Finding Aid for University of Michigan. Buildings and Grounds Dept.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Buildings and Grounds Dept. (University of Michigan) records 1913-1956, 1922-1924
University of Michigan. Buildings and Grounds Dept.
1 oversize folders
3.5 linear feet (in 5 boxes)
Photographs, negatives, and lantern slides of university buildings, including photos of each building owned by the university in 1923, and detailed construction photos of Angell Hall, West Medical Building (later renamed C.C. Little Science Building), Central Heating Plant, University Hospital (Old Main). Also includes houses surrounding campus, heating tunnels, and Buildings and Grounds vehicles, horse teams, employees and equipment.
87135 Bimu D13 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred by Buildings and Grounds (Donor No. 980) and through Plant Extension (Donor No. 6751) in several accessions. In addition records have also been accessioned through Donor Nos. 4361 and 5582.
The collection is open for research.
During the late 1800s the maintenance of the buildings and grounds on the campus of the University of Michigan was the job of a group of loosely organized workers. Janitorial services were not provided by a central department. Instead, janitors worked under the direction of the Business Office. In 1910 James Harmon Marks was appointed the first superintendent of Buildings and Grounds. Under the guidance of Marks, Buildings and Grounds became a centralized department, to which many previously independent units reported. The main focus of the department was to maintain the interiors and exteriors of buildings and to deliver coal for heating the university's buildings. In the 1920s Buildings and Grounds constructed a series of tunnels throughout the campus which connected all of the campus buildings to the Washington Street Power Plant. The tunnels enabled Buildings and Grounds to provide all of the heat and electricity for the buildings from a single source. In subsequent years the department began to oversee many other university units related to the expansion of the campus. To reflect Buildings and Grounds' changing role the Board of Regents changed the Buildings and Grounds Department name in 1930 to the Plant Extension Services Department. The duties of the newly organized Plant Extension Services included serving as a liaison between the university units responsible for financial accountability, construction engineering, engineering services, the university architect's office and the university planner's office. In addition the department monitors and coordinates all new construction as well as the expansion of existing buildings.
The Buildings and Grounds record group is largely composed of photographs which document the period of expansion that began when Marion L. Burton took office as the president of the university in 1920. That same year, the Board of Regents appointed a committee to evaluate the spatial needs of the university. In January 1921 the committee reported to Burton and the Regents that the university would need $19,000,000 for a suitable building project to commence. The university petitioned the state legislature and was given a large portion of the money. A committee was created which oversaw all of the plans for expansion. The committee was called "the committee on the comprehensive building program," but is generally referred to as "the committee of five;" its members were: Regent William L. Clements, President Burton, Secretary Shirley Wheeler Smith, architect Albert Kahn and Professor John Shepard. The buildings that were constructed under the initial wave of expansion were: East Medical (Clarence Cook Little), Literary Building (Angell Hall), East Engineering Building, Model (University) High School (School of Education), New Physics Laboratory, the expansion of University Hospital (Old Main) and the addition to the Dental Building. The university bought many of the surrounding houses and properties in order for some of the new buildings to be constructed. The university expansion peaked the interest of private donors which resulted in the money that built the Clements Library and Yost Field House. With the success of the first phase of building the university again asked the state legislature for more funds to continue the building efforts. The state granted the university money which resulted in the construction of an addition to the power plant. At the same time more donations led to the construction of the Lawyer's Club and Couzens Hall. President Burton made a third appeal for money to the state, but prior to it being granted, he died. His request was approved and the funds resulted in the building of a new museum and the Architecture Building (Lorch Hall) in 1925.
Additional material relating to the Buildings and Grounds Department and President Burton's building projects can be found in the University of Michigan Plant Extension Services record group as well as the proceedings of the Board of Regents and the papers of the presidents.
The record group for the Buildings and Grounds Department is primarily comprised of visual materials that document the construction projects which the department oversaw. The bulk of the records are from the 1920s, with the photographs composing the largest portion of the collection. Non-original images of some university buildings from the 1800s are also included.
The records are arranged into six series: Architectural Drawings, Photo Albums, Photographs, Lantern Slides, Glass Plate Negatives, and Topographical Maps.
Subjects:
Alumni Memorial Hall (University of Michigan); Angell Hall (University of Michigan); Architecture.; Chemistry Building (University of Michigan); Dental Building (University of Michigan); East Engineering Building (University of Michigan); East Medical Building (University of Michigan); East Physics Building (University of Michigan); Economics Building (University of Michigan); Health Service Building (University of Michigan); Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Natural Science Building (University of Michigan); Tappan Hall (University of Michigan); University High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan--Maps.; West Engineering Building (University of Michigan); West Medical Building (University of Michigan); West Physics Building (University of Michigan)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alumni Memorial Hall (University of Michigan); Angell Hall (University of Michigan); Architecture.; Chemistry Building (University of Michigan); Dental Building (University of Michigan); East Engineering Building (University of Michigan); East Medical Building (University of Michigan); East Physics Building (University of Michigan); Economics Building (University of Michigan); Health Service Building (University of Michigan); Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Natural Science Building (University of Michigan); Tappan Hall (University of Michigan); University High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; HVAC systems--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; North Campus (University of Michigan); Tunnels--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Architectural Drawings, 1927
  The first series Architectural Drawings (1927) consists of the floor plans for several university buildings. They are arranged alphabetically by the name of the building.
  - Alumni Memorial Hall 1927 (Box 1)
  - Angell Hall 1927 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - Dental Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - East Engineering Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - East Medical Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - East Physics Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - Economics Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - Health Services Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - Hill Auditorium 1927 (Box 1)
  - Library 1927 (Box 1)
  - Natural Science Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - Tappan Hall 1927 (Box 1)
  - University Elementary School specifications 1929 (Box 1)
  - University High School 1927 (Box 1)
  - Waterman Gymnasium specifications 1916 and 1923 (Box 1)
  - West Engineering Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - West Medical Building 1927 (Box 1)
  - West Physics Building 1927 (Box 1)
- Photo Albums, 1923-1940
  The series Photo Albums (1923-1940) contains two bound 8x10 photo albums. The first is a scrapbook that was assembled by Buildings and Grounds. It contains 5x7 photographs of every campus building that was in use in 1923. There are also photographs of the houses that were located on the property acquired for new construction. In addition to photographs the album contains a fact sheet listing building specifications, construction costs and the architect. The second album (labeled WPA) contains photographs of the construction of an addition onto the Health Services Building, which was completed in 1938.
  - Buildings and Grounds Scrapbook 1923
    (*indicates a negative is available in envelopes following the volume)
    - University Hall (Box 1)
    - Law Building (Box 1)
    - Alumni Memorial Hall (Box 1)
    - Museum* (Box 1)
    - Tappan Hall (Box 1)
    - President's House* (Box 1)
    - Engineering Shops* (Box 1)
    - New Engineering Building (West Hall) (Box 1)
    - Medical Building (Box 1)
    - Chemistry Building (Box 1)
    - Barbour Gymnasium* (Box 1)
    - Natural Science (Box 1)
    - Pharmacology Building (Box 1)
    - Economics Building* (Box 1)
    - Physical Laboratory (Box 1)
    - Sub-Station (Box 1)
    - Old Campus Boiler House (Box 1)
    - Old Campus Fire Station* (Box 1)
    - Old West Hall* (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Office (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Surgical Ward (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Palmer Ward (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Medical Ward (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Psychopathic Ward* (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Power House (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Dermatology Ward (Box 1)
    - University Hospital-Contagious Ward (Box 1)
    - Homeopathic Hospital* (Box 1)
    - Homeopathic Administration Building (Box 1)
    - Dental Building (Box 1)
    - Laundry Building* (Box 1)
    - Forestry Experiment Station* (Box 1)
    - Hill Auditorium (Box 1)
    - Newberry Residence (Box 1)
    - Martha Cook Building (Box 1)
    - Michigan Union (Box 1)
    - Power Plant (Box 1)
    - Hatcher Library (Box 1)
    - Storehouse (Box 1)
    - Children's Annex (Box 1)
    - Interns Home* (Box 1)
    - Maternity Ward* (Box 1)
    - Nurses Home* (Box 1)
    - Nurses Home #1* (Box 1)
    - Nurses Home #2* (Box 1)
    - House 114 So. 14th* (Box 1)
    - House 118 So. 14th* (Box 1)
    - House 1209 Geddes* (Box 1)
    - House, 1227 Washtenaw* (Box 1)
    - House 901 N. University* (Box 1)
    - House 907 N. University* (Box 1)
    - House 911 N. University* (Box 1)
    - House 236 12th St.* (Box 1)
    - House 113 So. 14th St.* (Box 1)
    - House 308 So. 14th St.* (Box 1)
    - House 1210 E. Washington* (Box 1)
    - House 1115 E. Huron* (Box 1)
    - House 226 So. Ingalls* (Box 1)
    - House 237 So. Ingalls* (Box 1)
  - Health Service PWA Project No. Mich. 1691-F Photo Album 1938-1940, 28 prints (in 1 bound album; no negatives) (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1913-1956
  Photographs (1913-1956) document the comprehensive building program that occurred in the early 1920s during the presidency of Marion Burton. According to the Board of Regents proceedings, Burton, at one point, requested to see photographs of buildings that other universities had constructed. It was perhaps that which inspired him to have his building project so well documented in photographs. The photographer (or photographers) of the pictures is somewhat of a mystery, but evidence suggests that Mr. Eugene Francisco, first of Lyndon Photographers and then with Francisco and Boyce Photographers, was responsible for taking many of the pictures. Some later photographs are stamped with the name of George Korwin, who was also a photographer in the Ann Arbor area. Of special interest are the photos of the construction of the Clements Library. The photos show how the building was built while the Old Engineering Building next to it was being razed. Also of special interest are the photos of the construction of Angell Hall. On the back of several of the prints are the content of descriptions of the pictures. Many of the later photographs, which document the initial stages of building of North Campus, will also be of interest. Some of the photos were taken on the roof of the Veterans Administration Hospital and provide an excellent birds-eye-view of the South side of the North Campus area along Fuller Road.
  The series contains many prints, the bulk of which have a matching original negative. The series also contains prints without negatives and some negatives without prints. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by the name of the building or subject that appears in them. There are three types of identifying systems in this series: bound prints with matching negatives, unbound prints with matching negatives, and lastly unbound, unmatched prints or negatives. The prints in the bound books have a number (1,2,3,4....) on the back. The negative that matches each print has a corresponding number on the envelope in which it is contained. The prints that are not bound and have a matching negative are labeled with both a letter and a number (A-1, A-2, A-3, A-4...). These are found on both the back of the print and on the envelope in which the negative is housed. The prints that have corresponding negatives are labeled alphabetically A,B,C... (if there are more than twenty-six than the system continues A-1, B-1, C-1...). The same system is used for negatives without matching prints. The envelopes are labeled either "print" or "negative" to differentiate.
  - Accident (auto) 1923 (Box 2)
  - Aerial View of Campus circa 1924 (Box 2)
  - Aeronautical Laboratories (Aerospace Engineering Complex) 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Memorial Hall (Museum of Art) undated (Box 2)
  - Angell Hall (Literary Building) 1922-1924, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Army Barracks, World War I era (Box 2)
  - Automotive Engineering Laboratory (Lay Automotive Laboratory) 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Botanical Gardens circa 1916 (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds-Shops 1923-1924, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds-Fire Main Test 1913-1914 (Box 2)
  - Burton Memorial Tower 1936, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Business Administration undated (Box 2)
  - Central Heating Plant and Heating Tunnels 1916 (Box 2)
  - Central Service and Stack Building (North Campus) 1954 (Box 2)
  - Clarence Cook Little (New Medical Building) 1923-1924, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Clements Library 1923 (Box 2)
  - Commencement at Ferry Field circa 1925-1940 (Box 2)
  - Cooley Memorial Laboratory 1955 (Box 2)
  - Corroded Water Pipes undated (Box 2)
  - Couzens Hall (Nurses Home) 1924-1925, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Dental Building 1922-1939 (Box 2)
  - Dermatology Ward undated (Box 2)
  - Detroit Edison Prints of Power Station 1926, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - East Engineering (East Hall) 1922-1923, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - East Quadrangle 1939 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Shops undated (Box 2)
  - (Old) Engineering-Razing 1921 (Box 2)
  - Field House Area Buildings undated (Box 2)
  - Football Stadium 1927 (Box 2)
  - Ford Nuclear Reactor 1955 (Box 2)
  - Gravel Pit circa 1924 (Box 2)
  - Health Services 1939 (Box 2)
  - Hill Auditorium-Interior and Exterior undated (Box 2)
  - Homeopathic Hospital (South Department Health Service) undated (Box 2)
  - Homes surrounding campus undated (Box 2)
  - Horse Teams undated (Box 2)
  - Ingalls Mall undated (Box 2)
  - Interns Home circa 1924 (Box 2)
  - Laundry circa 1934 (Box 3)
  - Law Department Building undated (Box 3)
  - Law Quadrangle 1929 (Box 3)
  - Lawyers Club 1924 (Box 3)
  - Lorch Hall (Architecture Building) undated (Box 3)
  - Maps of the University 1919-1941 (Box 3)
  - Martha Cook Dormitory undated (Box 3)
  - (Old) Mason Hall 1841-1849 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Union Addition 1936-1937 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Photos-Bound Album, 2 folders
    - Tunnels 1923-1924 (Box 3)
    - Animal House 1924 (Box 3)
    - Clements Library undated (Box 3)
    - Memorial Church of Christ 1924 (Box 3)
    - Waterman Gymnasium Addition 1924 (Box 3)
  - Mosher Jordan Hall 1930 (Box 3)
  - Natural Science Building (New Science) 1914 (Box 3)
  - North Campus: Utilities, Grading and General View 1955 (Box 3)
  - Northwood Apartments, Group I 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Northwood Apartments, Group II 1956 (Box 3)
  - Newberry Residence Addition 1934 (Box 3)
  - (Old) Nurses Home undated (Box 3)
  - Old Medical Building-West Section After 1911 Fire, 1911 (Box 3)
  - Old University Library undated (Box 3)
  - Phoenix Memorial Laboratory 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Physics and Astronomy (Randall) 1922 (Box 3)
  - Power Plant 1920-1925, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Power Plant-Washington Street Storage Addition undated (Box 3)
  - President's House Addition 1920 (Box 3)
  - Printing and Warehouse Building 1955 (Box 3)
  - Rackham (Graduate School) 1936-1938 (Box 3)
  - Stockwell Hall 1939 (Box 3)
  - Trees Moved by Buildings and Grounds circa 1932 (Box 3)
  - Tunnels 1923-1936 (Box 3)
  - University Hall-Exterior and Interior Decay undated (Box 3)
  - University (Model) High School 1922-1923, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - University Hospital (Old Main) 1923-1934, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Vertebrate Genetics Research Laboratory-exterior 1931 (Box 3)
  - Victor C. Vaughan Residence 1939 (Box 3)
  - Waterman Gymnasium Remodelling 1916 (Box 3)
  - Waterman Gymnasium undated (Box 3)
  - West Engineering undated (Box 3)
  - West Engineering Annex-After Fire 1937 (Box 3)
  - West Quadrangle 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Unidentified
    - Campus Area Street Scenes circa 1924 (Box 3)
    - Construction Sites circa 1922-1924 (Box 3)
    - Equipment undated (Box 3)
    - Interiors and Exteriors undated (Box 3)
    - University Employees circa 1923 (Box 3)
- Lantern Slides, 1927-1941
  Lantern Slides (1927-1941) compose the fourth series. The slides are in numerical order and the negatives that match the slides are filed with the Photograph series and contain the number corresponding to the slide. If there is no matching negative, it is noted on the envelope containing the slide. The slides are of the interiors and exteriors of campus buildings. In addition, the end of the series contains slides of Buildings and Grounds employees, who appear to be members of the janitorial staff.
  - 1-Lawyers Club (interior) (Box 4)
  - 2-Angell Hall (Literary Building) (Box 4)
  - 3-Angell Hall (Literary Building) (Box 4)
  - 4-Martha Cook Dormitory (Box 4)
  - 5-East Quadrangle; Typical Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 6-East Quadrangle; Lounge 1939 (Box 4)
  - 7-Football Stadium 1927 (Box 4)
  - 8-(Old) Health Services Ward (Box 4)
  - 9-(New) Health Services Ward (Box 4)
  - 10-Kellogg Institute and Health Services 1939 (Box 4)
  - 11-Law Quadrangle-Aerial View (Box 4)
  - 12-Lorch Hall (Architecture Building) (Box 4)
  - 13-(Old) Mason Hall; South Wing, [1841-1849] (Box 4)
  - 14-Map of the University 1919 (Box 4)
  - 15-Map of the University 1921 (Box 4)
  - 16-Map of the University 1923 (Box 4)
  - 17-Map of the University 1926 (Box 4)
  - 17.5-Map of the University 1940 (Box 4)
  - 18-Map of the University 1941 (Box 4)
  - 19-Alumni Memorial Hall (Museum of Art) (Box 4)
  - 20-Stockwell Hall-Aerial View 1939 (Box 4)
  - 21-Stockwell Hall; Lobby 1939 (Box 4)
  - 22-Stockwell Hall; Serving Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 23-Stockwell Hall; Library 1939 (Box 4)
  - 24-Stockwell Hall; Lounge 1939 (Box 4)
  - 24.5-Stockwell Hall; Lobby 1939 (Box 4)
  - 25-Victor C. Vaughan Residence 1939 (Box 4)
  - 26-West Quadrangle; Aerial View 1939 (Box 4)
  - 27-West Quadrangle; Game Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 28-West Quadrangle; Typical Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 29-West Quadrangle; Dining Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 30-West Quadrangle; Serving Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 31-West Quadrangle; Trunk Room 1939 (Box 4)
  - 32-West Quadrangle; Lounge 1939 (Box 4)
  - 33-View in former residence on site of West Quadrangle 1938 (Box 4)
  - 34-View in former residence on site of West Quadrangle 1938 (Box 4)
  - 35-Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1937 (Box 4)
  - 36-University Hall, [1873] (Box 4)
  - 37-Clements Library (Box 4)
  - 38-Burton Tower 1936 (Box 4)
  - 39-Angell Hall (Literary Building) (Box 4)
  - 40-Hill Auditorium-exterior (Box 4)
  - 41-View of Campus-Aerial, [1863] (Box 4)
  - 42-View of Campus-Aerial, [1869] (Box 4)
  - 43-View of Campus-Aerial, [1880] (Box 4)
  - 44-View of Campus-Aerial 1936 (Box 4)
  - 45-View of Campus-Aerial undated (Box 4)
  - 46-View of Campus-Aerial undated (Box 4)
  - 47-Law Quadrangle (Box 4)
  - 48-Law Quadrangle (Box 4)
  - 49-Law Quadrangle (Box 4)
  - 50-Unidentified-Campus Area Street Scene (Box 4)
  - 51-Unidentified-Campus Area Street Scene (Box 4)
  - 52-Unidentified-Campus Area Street Scene (Box 4)
  - 53-Unidentified-Exterior (Box 4)
  - 54-Unidentified-Exterior (Box 4)
  - 55-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 56-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 57-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 58-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 59-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 60-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 61-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 62-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 63-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 64-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 65-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 66-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 67-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 68-Unidentified-University Employees (Box 4)
  - 69-"Doc" Nagle (Medical School Custodian) (Box 4)
- Glass Plate Negatives, 1918-1922 and undated
  The series, Glass Plate Negatives (1918-1922, undated) are in numerical order, many of the negatives match prints that are in the Photograph series. The prints that match glass negatives are labeled as such and each is given the number of the glass plate negative to which they correspond.
  - 1-East Engineering (East Hall) (Box 5)
  - 2-Buildings and Grounds-Shops (Box 5)
  - 3-Laundry Truck (Box 5)
  - 4-Clements Library 1922 (Box 5)
  - 5-Unidentified Exterior (Box 5)
  - 6-Tunnels (Box 5)
  - 7-Unidentified-Construction Site (Box 5)
  - 8-Unidentified-Equipment [furnace?] (Box 5)
  - 9-Buildings and Grounds-Shops (Box 5)
  - 10-University Hospital-Main Entrance (Box 5)
  - 11-Power Plant (Box 5)
  - 12-Dermatology Ward (Box 5)
  - 13-Dermatology Ward (Box 5)
  - 14-Dental Building Addition 1922 (Box 5)
  - 15-Unidentified Equipment [sinks] (Box 5)
  - 16-Unidentified Equipment [sewing machine] (Box 5)
  - 17-Army Barracks (Box 5)
  - 18-Army Barracks (Box 5)
  - 19-Army Barracks (Box 5)
  - 20-Army Barracks (Box 5)
  - 21-Unidentified-Street Scene 1922 (Box 5)
  - 22-Unidentified-House (Box 5)
  - 23-Unidentified House (Box 5)
  - 24-Unidentified House 1922 (Box 5)
  - 25-Unidentified House (Box 5)
  - 26-Unidentified House (Box 5)
  - 27-Unidentified House (Box 5)
  - 28-University Hospital-Main Entrance (Box 5)
  - 29-University Hospital-Main Entrance (Box 5)
  - 30-Unidentified-Construction Site (Box 5)
  - 31-Homeopathic Hospital (ROTC) (Box 5)
  - 32-Homeopathic Hospital (ROTC) (Box 5)
  - 33-Dermatology Ward (Box 5)
  - 34-Botanical Gardens (Box 5)
  - 35-Chemistry Building (Box 5)
  - 36-Chemistry Building (Box 5)
  - 37-Old Engineering Building (Box 5)
  - 38-Unidentified-Interior [interior] (Box 5)
  - 39-Unidentified Builds and Grounds Shops (Box 5)
  - 40-Observatory-Aerial View 1922 (Box 5)
  - 41-View of Campus-Aerial 1922 (Box 5)
  - 42-View of Campus Area undated (Box 5)
  - 43-Army Barracks, W.W.I era (Box 5)
  - 44-Army Barracks, W.W.I era (Box 5)
  - 45-Army Barracks, W.W.I era (Box 5)